Guide to the Richard McGee Morse Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard McGee Morse papers
1955-1985
1962-1972
MS 1719
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
The papers consist of correspondence and subject files documenting the professional life of Richard McGee Morse, historian and educator, while at Yale University.
Morse, Richard M. (Richard McGee), 1922-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bryn Mawr College, 1996
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research, with the exception of the correspondence series, which is restricted until January 1, 2053.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, 1955-1985. II. Organizations, 1959-1972. III. Yale University, 1964-1977. IV. Subject Files, 1963-1984.
Biographical / Historical
Richard McGee Morse received his B.A. from Princeton in 1943. He then studied at Columbia University, where he received his M.A. in 1947 and Ph.D. in 1952. Morse became associate professor of history at Yale University in 1962, and professor in 1963. He served as chairman of the Council on Latin American Studies in the 1963-1964 academic year. Morse was also a fellow of Silliman College until his departure from Yale in 1972.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence and subject files documenting the professional life of Richard McGee Morse, historian and educator, while at Yale University.
Morse, Richard M. (Richard McGee), 1922-2001; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History
- Correspondence, 1955-1985; Series I
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is restricted until Jan 1, 2053.
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of the correspondent.
  - A [general], 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alden, Dauril, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Andic, Fuat, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anglade, Christian, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Apter, David, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B [general], 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barnes, William, 1965, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bigelow, Donald, 1964, 1966, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bissainthe, Max, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Blondel, Jean, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Botsford, Keith, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bourne, James, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brewster, Kingman, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Buarque de Holanda, Sergio, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - C [general], 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cahn, Herbert, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Candido, Antonio, 1965-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cardoso, Fernando, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Caro Baroja, Julio, 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Carr, Raymond, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Castedo, Leopoldo, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chaves, Jose, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cline, Howard, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cooper, Donald, 1963, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Corten, Andre, 1967, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cortes Conde, Roberto, 1966-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Culver, John, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cunningham, W. J., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - D [general], 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Davidson, David, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Davis, Tom, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Deas, Malcolm, 1963- 1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - de Jong, Theo P.M., 1964-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Duran, Manuel, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dwyer, John, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - E [general], 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Elliot, Jorge, 1965-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Ely, Roland, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - F [general], 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Farkas, Thomaz, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Fernandez, Florestan, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Fernandez, Oscar, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Flynn, Peter, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Foracchi, Marialice, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Friedmann, John, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Fulbright, J. W., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Fullerton, Peter, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - G [general], 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gakenheimer, Ralph, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Garcia-Zamor, Jean-Claude, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 50 - 51)
  - Genovese, Dominick Eugene, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Gerety, Thomas, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Gibson, Charles, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Gillingham, Peter, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Goldman, Frank Ferry, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Gongora, Mario, 1966, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Gordon, Richard S., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Greene, Donald, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Griffin, Charles C., 1964-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Gschaedler, Andre, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - H [general], 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Hahner, June, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Hale, Charles, 1965-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Halperin, Tulio, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Hanke, Louis, 1963- 1968 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Hardeman, Nicholas, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Hardoy, Jorge, 1955, 1965-1972 (Box 2, Folder 68 - 70)
  - Harrison, John, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Heinl, R. D., Jr., 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Hoetink, Harry, 1963-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Hoskins, John, 1964-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Howe, Arthur, 1963, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Howe, Walter, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Huth, Arno, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - J [general], 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Jaworski Cardenas, Helan, 1966, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Johnson, Harold, 1965-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - K [general], 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Kenworthy, Eldon, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Knox, A. J. G., 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - L [general], 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Lamar, Howard, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - LaPalombara, Joseph, 1967-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Leonard, Irving, 1963-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Lipson, Leon, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - M [general], 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Mackay, Duncan, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - MacLeod, Murdo, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Manigat, Leslie, 1963-1966, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Manning, Bayliss, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Mathews, Tom, 1967-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Mattelart, Armand, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - McGreevey, William, 1966-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Moreira, Sylvia, 1966-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Morner, Magnus, 1964, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - N-O [general], 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - P [general], 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Paek, Pong Hyon, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Pearson, Shelly, 1966, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Pierson, Donald, 1965-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Poppino, Rollie, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Q [general], 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Quijano, Anibal, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - R [general], 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Reverter-Pezet, Guillermo, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Reynolds, Clark, 1965-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Rodriguez-Monegal, Emir, 1969-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 110 - 111)
  - Rozwenc, Edwin, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - S [general], 1963-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Safford, Frank, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Salazar, Edgard, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Santos, Milton, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Schwab, William, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Schwartz, Stuart, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Seckinger, Ron, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Shapleigh, Alexander, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Sherlock, Philip, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Silvert, Kal, 1957, 1966-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 122 - 123)
  - Skidmore, Thomas, 1964, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Smith, Betsy, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Spalding, Karen, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Sparks, Archie, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Steger, Hanns-Albert, 1965-1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Stoetzer, Carlos, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Suddard, Adrienne V., 1969-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Szyszlo, Fernando, 1965-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - T [general], 1964-1969 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Towner, Lawrence, 1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Trowbridge, James, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Uribe, Andres, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - V [general], 1963, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Villegas, Jose, 1960-1961, 1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - W [general], 1963-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Walch, Timothy, 1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Wauchope, Robert, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Whitaker, Arthur, 1963, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - White, Byron, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Woodhouse, Chase, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Woods, Katherine, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Wool, Robert, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Xirau, Ramon, 1961, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Y [general], 1965, 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Z [general], 1963, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - Unidentified, 1965-1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 149)
- Organizations, 1959-1972; Series II
  The series contains materials related to various professional organizations with which Morse was involved. The series is arranged in alphabetical order by name of the organization.
  - ACCION, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - American Association of University Presses, 1962-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 2 - 4)
  - American Association of University Presses Latin American Translation Program, 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - American Faculty Interchange Program, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - American Historical Association Program Committee, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 7 - 8)
  - Beveridge Award, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Fellowship Program, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Center for Inter-American Relations, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - City Planning Department, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Committee on the International Exchange of Persons, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Committee for the Study of Mankind, 1959, 1962-1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Comparative colonization symposium, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Congreso Internacional de Americanistas, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Education and world affairs, 1965-1969, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Foreign Area Fellowship Program, 1964-1971, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Foreign Service Institute, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1967-1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Hispanic American Historical Review Editorial Board, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Hispanic Foundation, 1962, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Inter-American University Foundation, 1968-1970, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - International Association for Cultural Freedom, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Latin American Research Review, 1965-1971, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Latin American Studies Association
    - Committee on Area Studies Centers, 1966-1970, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Committee on Argentine Refugees, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Nominations Committee and Conference Committee, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Program Committee, 1968, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Thirty Eighth Congress of Americanists, 1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Yale University, 1964-1977; Series III
  The series is divided into two sections: administration and teaching. The administration section contains materials related to the faculty committees and organizations Morse worked with while at Yale. The teaching section contains exams and syllabi from courses Morse taught.
  - Administration
    - Board of Permanent Officers and Graduate School Faculty, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Concilium on International and Area Studies, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Council on Comparative and European Studies, 1966-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Council on Geographic Studies, 1965-1967, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Council on International Relations, 1965- 1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Council on Latin American Studies, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Department of Anthropology, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Department of Economics, 1967-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Economic Growth Center, 1963-1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - International Office, 1969-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Teaching
    - Exams, 1964-1968 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - History 28a/Study of the City 10a, 1967- 1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - History 85b, 1966, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - History 206b, 1967-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - History 208b and 298a, 1966-1970 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Language instruction, 1977, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Subject files, 1963-1984; Series IV
  The series is arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Bulletins [of other universities], 1965- 1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Conference on social structure, 1968, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Fellowships and training, 1963-1968, undated (Box 8, Folder 3 - 4)
  - Fulbright Scholarships, 1970, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Job openings, placements, 1964-1972, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Latin American teaching fellowships, 1970, undated (Box 8, Folder 7 - 8)
  - Migration, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 10)